Guide to the Lawrence Gilman Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lawrence Gilman papers
1886-1971
1913-1939
YCAL MSS 407
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.63
(2 boxes)
The papers consist of letters to Lawrence Gilman from various writers, poets, editors, and musicians, including Winifred Welles, Carl Van Vechten, Winston Churchill, John Farrar, Otto Klemperer, Marian MacDowell, H. L. Mencken, Ezra Pound, Bruno Walter, John Butler Yeats, and William Butler Yeats. A small amount of letters are from Gilman family members and an unidentified correspondent. Other papers include a draft of Gilman's "Bach the Great Modern," two notebooks, and clippings.
Gilman, Lawrence, 1878-1939
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Elizabeth L. Anderson, 1951-1984.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Lawrence Gilman
Lawrence Gilman, American author and music critic, was born on July 5, 1878 in Flushing, New York to Arthur Coit Gilman and Bessie Lawrence Gilman. His great uncle was the educator Daniel Coit Gilman. He studied at Collins Street Classical School in Hartford, CT, where he exhibited great talent for music theory and proficiency with several instruments. He worked for the New York Herald from 1896 to 1898 and as a music critic for Harper's Weekly, where he advanced to the position of managing editor, which he held from 1901 to 1913. Gilman worked as a general arts critic for the North American Review from 1915 to 1923, and for the Herald Tribune from 1925. On August 1, 1904, he married Elizabeth Wright Walter, with whom he had one child, Elizabeth "Betty" Lawrence Gilman in 1905. Gilman died on September 8, 1939 in Sugar Hill, New Hampshire.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of letters to Lawrence Gilman from various writers, poets, editors, artists, and musicians, including Winifred Welles, Carl Van Vechten, Winston Churchill, John Farrar, Otto Klemperer, Marian MacDowell, H. L. Mencken, Ezra Pound, Bruno Walter, John Butler Yeats, and William Butler Yeats. A small amount of letters are from Gilman family members and an unidentified correspondent. Other papers include a draft of Gilman's "Bach the Great Modern," two notebooks, and clippings.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1886-1953. II. Writings and Other Papers, 1921-1971.
Authors, American -- 20th Century; Music critics -- 20th Century; Churchill, Winston, 1871-1947; Gilman, Lawrence, 1878-1939; Klemperer, Otto, 1885-1973; MacDowell, Marian, 1857-1956; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964; Walter, Bruno, 1876-1962; Welles, Winifred, 1893-1939; Yeats, John Butler, 1839-1922; Yeats, W. B. (William Butler), 1865-1939
- Correspondence, 1886-1953; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Adams, Franklin Pierce, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aiken, George, 1940 January 22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anderson, Elizabeth, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes draft of poem, "From a Kitten to Her Mistress"
  - Bangs, John Kendrick, 1913 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Barber, Samuel, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Barrère, Georges, 1938 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Beaux, Elizabeth, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Benét, Stephen Vincent, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bennett, Arnold, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bok, Mary L.C., 1932 January 20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bolton, Laetitia, 1935 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    On behalf of Little, Brown & Company
  - Bori, Lucrezia, 1937 December 29, 1947 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bowen, Catherine, 1935 June 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bridges, Robert, 1915 November 5, 1916 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Churchill, Winston, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Damrosch, Walter, 1925, 1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Davis, Bette, 1940 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Einstein, Alfred, 1939 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Farrar, John, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Field, Rachel, 1934-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Finck, Henry T., 1909 January 11, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Flagler, H.H., 1934 October 22 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Fremstad, Olive, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Garland, Hamlin, 1917, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Gilder, Richard Watson, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Gilman family, 1886, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes letters from Mrs. Edward C. Gilman and Miss Carrie T. Gilman
  - Goossens, Eugene, 1936 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Grant, Perry Stickney, 1920 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hackett, Francis, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hadow, Sir W. Henry, 1929 December 3 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hastings, Fanny de Groot, 1940-1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes drafts and clippings of poems by Hastings
  - Hermann, Bernard, 1939 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hertz, Alfred, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Howells, William Dean, 1906, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Johnson, Edward, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Keith, Agnes Newton, 1946 December 13 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Kirkpatrick, John, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Klemperer, Otto, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Le Gallienne, Richard, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lippmann, Walter, 1915 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lodge, Oliver J., 1917 March 29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lowell, Amy, 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - MacDowell, Marian, 1904, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Photocopies of original letters. Includes 1972 letters from Elizabeth Anderson to Yale regarding the photocopies
  - Mason, Daniel Gregory, 1937 November 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Matzenaur, Margaret, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - McArthur, Edwin D., 1939, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Melchior, Lauritz, 1937 November 17 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Mencken, H. L., 1916, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Moore, Douglas, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newman, Ernest, 1933 February 20 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Norris, Charles G., undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ormandy, Eugene, 1936, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Parker, Henry T., 1923, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Phelps, William Lyon, 1916-1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Pollock, Channing, 1931 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Pound, Ezra, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Reiner, Fritz, 1951 March 4 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Rockefeller, John D., Jr., and Abby, 1938, 1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Schauffler, Robert Haven, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Seymour, George Dudley, 1929 October 7 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Shearer, Harold H., 1921, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sherman, S. P., 1925 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Speyer, Leonora, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stokowski, Leopold, 1921-1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stokowski, Olga Samaroff, 1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Strong, Templeton, 1914 April 24 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Taylor, Deems, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Thompson, Oscar, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Tibbett, Lawrence, 1935 June 13 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Torrence, Ridgely, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Toscanini, Walter, 1953 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Vallas, Leon, 1933 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Van Loon, Hendrik, 1939 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 1921 February 16 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Wagner, Siegfried, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Wagner, Winifred, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Walter, Bruno, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Welles, Winifred, 1916-1939 (Box 1, Folder 10-13)
    Includes a folder of poem drafts
  - West, Rebecca, 1924-1927, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Wilson, Woodrow, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Winter, William, 1911 April 9 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Woollcott, Alexander, 1911-1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Wyatt, Edith Franklin, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Yeats, John Butler, 1915 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Yeats, William Butler, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Young, Stark, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Ziegler, Edward, 1923-1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Previously Uncat ZA File 42
  - Correspondence with Lawrence and Elizabeth Gilman, photograph of Bessie Amelia Lawrence Gilman, and the pamphlet "An Analysis of the Drama of the Bibelung's Ring" by Julia S. Gilman, 1894-1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Includes letters to the Gilmans from Minna Lederman (photocopy), Constance Lindsay Skinner
    Previously Uncat Za File 47
  - Unidentified correspondence, 1956 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Writings and Other Papers, 1921-1971; Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  - Draft and outline for "Bach the Great Modern", 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Includes correspondence with Otto Strobe
  - Two notebooks with writings and clippings, 1921-1934 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
    Includes source materials for quotations; clippings and writings are pasted and laid in.
  - Clippings, 1935-1971 (Box 1, Folder 23)